<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Chase Nutile]]></title>
  <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-10T12:38:43-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chase Nutile]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[t5-ruby-classes]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t5-ruby-classes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T17:05:23-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t5-ruby-classes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We did a lot of work with ruby classes this week.  I&rsquo;m going to do my best to explain them to you with real world examples, in this blog.  I hope this proves useful.  Thanks for reading!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Explain when, why, and how to use classes</p>

<p>I would use classes whenever there was a real world object that needed to be represented through my code.  I would generally break classes into the brodest terms possible.  For instance, a class named Vehicle seems more appropriate than a class name 2014 Honda Civic.  More specific instances like a 2014 Honda Civic should be created with either methods or vairables.</p>

<p>Explain how data structures and classes can model a real-world object</p>

<p>I would compare ruby classes to cookbooks, with ruby methods being the recipes.  For instance, you can have a class called BBQ and within it you could create several methods that make BBQ dishes.  Ribs, brisket, sausage links, cornbread.  These could all be methods in the class BBQ.  Later you could even split cornbread into a different class called Sides if you wanted to.  Classes are extremely helpful in Ruby precisely because they make it so easy to model real world objects in a digital environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[c5-feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c5-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T17:02:51-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c5-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Feedback is a vital part of the pairing process.  This blog post is me attempting to explain the benefits, and my experience, with pairing and some of the feedback I&rsquo;ve received.  I&rsquo;ve had a chance to work with a ton of awesome people in DBC so far and I consider myself very lucky.  Thanks for reading!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Identify one emotion that arose during a pairing session</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had a ton of fun pairing thus far!  All of my pair partners have been very respectful and helpful.  I feel very lucky to have all these awesome new friends!</p>

<p>Describe kind, actionable, and specific feedback</p>

<p>Kind, actionable, and specific feedback is an essential part of the pairing process.  I feel all the feedback I&rsquo;ve received was KAS.</p>

<p>Discuss the feeling of vulnerability when pairing and reading feedback</p>

<p>I always feel vulnerable.  I think it&rsquo;s a part of being an honest person.  There&rsquo;s always this idea that people know exactly who and what you are, and could use it against you at any time.  Pairing is no different.  The only experience I have writing code is a C++ course I took at UIC in 2012 so I&rsquo;m pretty insecure about my skills as a programmer.  Also, I&rsquo;m definitely not the type to pretend that I&rsquo;m good at something when I&rsquo;m not.  Like I stated above: everyone has been totally kind in their feedback.  Vulnerability is always a part of stuff like this.  I just do my best to not let it control me.</p>

<p>Was something frustrating and difficult for you?</p>

<p>I had a lot of trouble expressing myself clearly in my pairing sessions.  I sometimes get so preoccupied with being nice that I freeze up and can&rsquo;t think.  It&rsquo;s difficult to pair with people you&rsquo;ve never met.  In person I think this problem would no longer exist.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[t4-enumerable-methods]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t4-enumerable-methods/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T17:01:35-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t4-enumerable-methods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just finished week 4 at Dev Bootcamp!  We did a lot of work with Ruby&rsquo;s public methods this week.  I used plenty of methods like .each,.each_slice,.count,.to_s,.to_a, etc., and will be explaining the Enumerable#map method to you in the following blog.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The map method is a method that can be very useful to rubyists in many ways.  What map does, is take and array, run the block given for every element of the array, and return a new array with new elments.  For instance, if I had the array [1,2,3,4], and I ran .map at the end of it like this: [1,2,3,4].map {|bango| bango + 1}, the new array would look like this: [2,3,4,5].  The map method iterated over every element of our original array, stored those elements in the variable &ldquo;bango&rdquo; and ran the block of code {bango + 1} for each.  It stores it&rsquo;s results in the corresponding indices of the new array.  Very useful!</p>

<p>So that&rsquo;s how the map method works.  Cool, right?  I should probably state here that Ruby has another method which does, literally, the same exact thing.  The name of this synonym method is #collect.  Ruby has these synonyms built in for easier use or transition from other languages.</p>

<p>I hope this explanation of #map was useful.  Thanks for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[c4-tech-issues]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c4-tech-issues/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:59:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c4-tech-issues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a blog post about male privilege in the tech world today.  I&rsquo;ll start with a disclaimer about some of the language used in this blog post then I&rsquo;ll move on to some statistics so we have a better grasp on the scope of this problem we&rsquo;re facing.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Disclaimer: I will be using words like patriarchy, sexism, and misogyny at differnt points throughout this blog post.  I&rsquo;m very careful about how I use these words and I think it&rsquo;s important that anyone else who would like to be a part of this conversation is equally thoughtful.  These words are not synonyms even though many times they are used as such.  Sexism, misogyny, patriarchy, and feminism are not words that should be thrown around lightly and they are NOT INTERCHANGEABLE.  Misogyny is defined as a hatred toward women and I will NEVER use that word when what I&rsquo;m actually talking about is male privilege or sexism.  This might seem nitpicky or semantic, but I assure you it is not.  In order to get everyone on board and truly affect change we need to understand these terms completely.  You should stop reading now and look all of those words up in the dictionary, if you haven&rsquo;t already done so.  If you are at all unsure of what these words mean or how they should be used, I strongly encourage you to study them a little more deeply.  As a male feminist in 2014 I will only be taken seriously if I&rsquo;ve done my homework and learned to talk about these things accurately.  I expect the same respect from anyone else wishing to engage in this conversation, whether they&rsquo;re women or men.</p>

<p>Alright, now that that&rsquo;s out of the way, let&rsquo;s jump into some stats.  According to Tech Republic, in 2013, women made up 26% of the computing workforce in the United States.  2% was made up of hispanic women, 3% were black women, and 5% were asian.  In 2013, women in the computing workforce earned 70 cents for every dollar a man made. In 2012, 57% of college graduates were women, yet only 12% of computer science degrees were obtained by women.  These are especially troubling numbers when you consider that women in western countries use the internet 17% more than men do, on average.</p>

<p>So inequality is a very real problem.  There&rsquo;s no arguing with that.  The point of contention, however, comes when you consider the reason why this is happening.  Why aren&rsquo;t women pursuing careers in computer science?</p>

<p>I look at the world around me or conjure memories of my childhood and can&rsquo;t help but notice that young women are frequently led in a different occupational direction than men.  Computer science is frequently portrayed as a man&rsquo;s job, whether it be in the media, in schools, or at home.  Young women just aren&rsquo;t being &ldquo;pushed&rdquo; in that direction.  Women are expected to be reserved in our society; to always be polite and always play by the rules.  This is the result of generations upon generations of patriarchy.  We all have an idea in our heads of what a &ldquo;typical&rdquo; computer scientist should look like.  Our society assigns masculinity to the job.  I can&rsquo;t help but think this is because computer science is difficult and in a patriarchal society, difficult things are left to men.  I implore you to break out of this line of thinking now.</p>

<p>The cultural indocrination of gender roles into children is unfortunate for many reasons.  Obviously, because it implies that the problem will take a full generation to fix.  Less obviously, because tech companies run by women, or who employ majority women, have been wildly succesful!  Women make great computer programmers and even better CEOs in the tech world.  We just don&rsquo;t associate the two things because we&rsquo;ve been taught to think otherwise.  Dow Jones did a study of tech companies over the past 17 years and showed that 7.1% of successful companies were headed by female executives, while only 3.1% of unsuccessful companies were run by women.</p>

<p>Women and young girls should be applauded for pragmaticism, technical skill, and leadership, just as much as men are today.  More so, we should all be applauded for empathy, compassion, and altruism.  When a young girl shows interest in technology she should be revered as a beautiful, strong, candidate for the tech companies of the future and she should be encouraged to pursue her passion unapologetically and without reserve.  If we do this, hopefully we can one day shift society&rsquo;s expectations of what a &ldquo;typical&rdquo; computer scientist is supposed to look like.</p>

<p>So what about the money?  It would be easy to say that women make 70% less than men because of sexism or mysogyny.  In many cases this is, no doubt, true.  But it&rsquo;s only one part of the problem.  A recent study at the University of Texas showed that women, on average, asked for $7,000 less than their male counterparts.  What&rsquo;s even more interesting about the UT study is that when asked to negotiate salary on behalf of a coworker, women and men asked for almost exactly the same amounts, regardless of the gender of the other party.  I can&rsquo;t help but think this is learned behavior and the direct result of patriarchy and male privilege.  We can change this in a generation or less, people!  I think more skills training on negotiation tactics for women in the workplace is a great place to start. But it&rsquo;s going to take everybody getting on board and men need to examine their roles in this problem and fix them too.  We need a long term, universal solution.  Not a bandaid.</p>

<p>As a feminist, this is an issue that I&rsquo;ve followed pretty closely for some time now.  I don&rsquo;t have any concrete answers, but I do know the problems that face us.  I think that&rsquo;s a great place to start.  I hope that future generations will feel comfortable transcending the barriers of gender roles in our society and stay true to themselves.  I know I have, and in many ways, my feminity has saved my life.  I&rsquo;d like to see a world where more men realize this and fields like the tech sector lose their aggressive, male-dominated ethos.</p>

<p>I was originally going to write this blog on net neutrality because it&rsquo;s another issue I&rsquo;ve followed closely and it seemed like a safer choice. I also wasn&rsquo;t sure I could do this issue justice without writing a thousand-page manifesto.  I haven&rsquo;t done it justice, honestly.  I&rsquo;m leaving so much unsaid for the sake of brevity.  Hopefully in the future I&rsquo;ll have a chance to meet with more people who have been directly affected by this issue and convey my ideas more exhaustively, in person.  Until then, I&rsquo;ll just leave it at this.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t ask for male privilege but at this point, I have it.  The best I can do is be aware of it, never try to exploit it, and take every chance given to dismantle it from the inside out.  It saddens me deeply that more people don&rsquo;t feel the same way.</p>

<p>Thank you for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[t3-array-hashes]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t3-array-hashes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:57:14-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t3-array-hashes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week at DBC we started the section on Ruby!  A lot of this week&rsquo;s material was review for me but I still learned a bunch and I definitely sharpened my skills a bit in the process.  I&rsquo;m going to write this blog about hashes and arrays.  Hopefully some of you find it useful!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Let&rsquo;s start by describing arrays.  An array is a list of elements that are grouped together and presented in an ordered list.  Every element in an array is representative of a single object.  These can be strings, numbers, variables &ndash; any object.  The Array class in ruby come with a ton of predefined methods which can be called on arrays to manipulate these elements.  Arrays are extremely useful for sorting and arranging large amounts of data quickly.</p>

<p>Arrays are created just like any other variable except that they accept a list of elements contained by brackets like so: my_array = [2,22,222];.  As I stated earlier, there are plenty of other ways to initialize and define an array.  I won&rsquo;t get into all of them here.</p>

<p>Now for hashes.  Hashes are very similar to arrays with one major difference and some smaller ones as well.  In an array every element corresponds to one specific value &ndash; not the case for hashes.  Every elment in a hash is a key-value pair.  Meaning you can have a with 10 different keys name &ldquo;dog&rdquo; that all hold a different value; names of dogs, breeds, dogs in the family, etc.  This is especially useful for sorting and organizing information.</p>

<p>Hashes, like arrays, have plenty of ways of being intitialized.  I&rsquo;ll show you the syntax which, in my opinion, is easiest to read here: pets = {&ldquo;dog&rdquo;: &ldquo;rat terrier&rdquo;, &ldquo;dog&rdquo;: &ldquo;shiba inu&rdquo;, &ldquo;cat&rdquo;: &ldquo;himalayan&rdquo;};.  Here, the hash named pets has two &ldquo;keys&rdquo; &ndash; dog and cat.  The values paired with these keys are different breeds.</p>

<p>You can see how organizing information in this way can be especially useful when coding web apps.  The use of both arrays and hashes allows the programmer a ton of felxibility and organization.  Warning: this can get really confusing, realy fast, and there is a ton to learn about both of these Classes in Ruby.  I&rsquo;ve barely scratched the surface here but I hope this has served as a useful primer on the subject.  Thanks for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[c2-thinking-style]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c2-thinking-style/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:54:15-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c2-thinking-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, everybody!  I&rsquo;m just finishing up week 3 at Dev Bootcamp and I thought I&rsquo;d share some of my thoughts here.  I be writing about my struggles, areas of confidence, learning/thinking styles and some of the social relationships I&rsquo;ve formed over the past 3 weeks.  Let&rsquo;s get started!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Before entering phase 0 at DBC I was asked to take a personal thinking quiz to identify my Gregorc thinking style.  The Gregorc lumps people into 4 different thinking stlyes: Concrete Sequential, Abstract Sequential, Concrete Random, and Abstract Random.  I was identified as Concrete Random.  This means I enjoy experimenting, taking risks, and using intuition to solve problems.</p>

<p>What are the benefits of being a Concrete Sequential thinker?  There are plenty.  Concrete Sequential thinkers respond well to trial-and-error approaches.  We love to tinker with things!  This has proved especially useful in the design portion of phase 0.  Tinkering with HTML and CSS was a big part of week 2 for me and I really enjoyed myself for most of it!</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s difficult about being a Concrete Random thinker?  Keeping detailed records.  This is an area where I&rsquo;ve always struggled.  I&rsquo;ve always taken a very &ldquo;organic&rdquo; approach to problem solving.  I like to dive straight in without hesitation and when I&rsquo;m feeling my &ldquo;flow,&rdquo; it will usually take a force of nature to stop me from working.  This is a tremendous asset in certain situations, but a horrible handicap in others.  When things need to stay perfectly organized and by-the-book, I struggle sometimes.  The best way for me to stay on top of this is to set up accountability meetings with my peers.</p>

<p>Over the past 3 weeks I&rsquo;ve had to be sure to constantly interact with other people in my cohort.  This forces me to stay organized and on topic for the sake of my peers.  Otherwise, I&rsquo;m just a rabbit in a hole and nothing is gonna bring me back to the surface.  Nothing.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve all heard it a million times before: software engineering is a team sport.  This has become increasingly clear to me over my time at DBC.  If I allow myself to become reclusive and totally independent I&rsquo;ll get lost in the chaos of my thought process.  Learning to work with others and keep myself organized for their benefit will be my greatest challenge to come.</p>

<p>Thanks for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[t2-css-design]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t2-css-design/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:50:48-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t2-css-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was a very tough week for me, technically.  CSS positioning gave me a ton of trouble and I definitely experienced my first &ldquo;rabbit hole&rdquo; situation.  It was not fun.</p>

<p>Anyway, I&rsquo;m going to explain the difference between margin, border, and padding in this week&rsquo;s technical blog.  I&rsquo;ll attach a helpful image below as well.  So here we go!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Let&rsquo;s do this from the inside out.  First up: padding.  Padding is the area that surrounds the content inside of a box model in html.  For instance, if you have a div tag with some text centered inside of it, the padding is the area between the text (also referred to as content) and the outside (border) of the div.  You can adjust the padding in css with the padding-left, padding-right, etc., atrributes.  You can also change all of them in one line with like this: padding: 10px 20px 10px 20px. The values begin with the top and go clockwise around the box.</p>

<p>Next up is border. The border is the line that contains the content and padding.  You can call it in css using border:.  You can assign different widths and colors to it, or you can make it solid, dashed, 3D, etc.</p>

<p>The margin is the area that surrounds the border.  Essentially, the area bertween the border and other html boxes.  It works in css much the same as padding does.  You can call margin-left, et al., or you can call all four values in one line.  I hope this was a helpful explanation of padding, border, and margin.  Thanks so much for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[c1-chefs-kitchen]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c1-chefs-kitchen/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T16:45:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/c1-chefs-kitchen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is no doubt in my mind that anyone can teach themselves how to use Rails.  Human beings are amazing creatures.  Time and time again they will surprise you with how much knowledge they can actually cram into those tiny little skulls of theirs!  That being said: a true craftsman goes beyond just these technical skills.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A true craftsman knows her customers, peers, apprentices and mentors from the inside out, and she strives to strengthen these relationships whenever possible.  Dev Bootcamp puts strong emphasis on these principles, and plans to fortify them in us, through the fire of a 9 week bootcamp environment.  I couldn&rsquo;t be happier to have this opportunity in front of me.</p>

<p>I know the people I&rsquo;m about to go on this journey with have a lot to teach me.  I hope that, in time, I can take that knowledge and pass it on to others.  This is looking like it&rsquo;s going to be the raddest thing I&rsquo;ve ever done!  I&rsquo;m stoked, to say the least; but I&rsquo;d be lying to you if I said I wasn&rsquo;t nervous.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s an awesome quote that I stumbled upon in Dave Hoover&rsquo;s book, &ldquo;Apprenticeship Patterns&rdquo; (this book is full of awesome quotes!): &ldquo;Working on real problems for real people is what hones the craft, not just doing it for self-satisfaction.&rdquo; - Ken Auer</p>

<p>I look forward to meeting you all in person one day.  Hopefully I&rsquo;ll have as much to teach to you, as I do to learn from you.  Thanks for taking the time to read this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[t1-git-blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t1-git-blog/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-09T15:08:57-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://b0xw00d.github.io/blog/2015/01/09/t1-git-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week I learned all about git and github at DBC.  Both are useful version control tools for web developers.  I&rsquo;ll do my best to clearly share what I&rsquo;ve learned with you here.  Bear with me now!
I&rsquo;ll start with version control.  Version control is a system for storing and sorting different iterations of a project.  This is helpful because it allows multiple people to be working on their own copies of the same files.  It also allows users to save older versions of code which they can revert back to, if needed.  Basically, if a mistake is made that breaks the project there are earlier, working versions of the program.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>So git is especially useful in helping users to keep track of changes they&rsquo;ve made to a project!  Great!  Now how do you use it?  I started by forking the project I wanted to use into my own github profile, then cloning it to my computer.  Forking a project is, essentially, making an exact copy of it that lives on your profile.  That way you can make changes without affecting the original files.  This fork will live on the web (your github profile).</p>

<p>In order to make changes on you computer, you need to clone this fork in your terminal, using git.  That will give you a local (on your hard drive) copy of the project so you can open it in Sublime and mess around a bit.  Any changes made can be saved as commits.  If you&rsquo;d like to view all the changes made to a file, the commit history is available to you by typing: git log; in the proper directory.  To add your commits to the main project you&rsquo;ll have to &ldquo;push&rdquo; it back to github.  This is done using: git push [REMOTENAME] [BRANCHNAME];.  To check your remote names, you can type: git remote -v;.</p>

<p>To track changes that have been made to the master branch of the project you can &ldquo;pull&rdquo; them from github.  This can be done with the following command in terminal: git pull [REMOTENAME] [BRANCHNAME];.  After running that code you can see what other coders have pushed to the project since your last pull.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s helpful to have both local and remote copies of these projects and the changes you&rsquo;ve made for the sake of collaboration.  These also serve as backup files.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot about git and github over the past couple of days and it&rsquo;s all pretty new to me.  I am by no means an expert.  I hope this was all clear enough though!  Thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
